I am a stone.
我是一塊石頭
I do not move.
我動也不動
Very slowly, I put snow in my mouth,
我慢慢地把雪塞進口
then he won't see my breath.
這樣，狼就看不見我的呼氣
I take my time. I let him come closer.
我耐心等待，等狼走近
I have only one bullet. I aim at his eye.
我只有一發子彈 我瞄準狼的眼睛
Very gently, my finger presses on the trigger.
手指放在扳掣上
I do not tremble.
我沒有發抖
I have no fear. I'm a big boy now.
我並不害怕 我已經是個大孩子了
Ready, Vassili?
準備，瓦西堙I
Now, Vassili. Fire!
瓦西堙A開槍！
Fire, Vassili! Fire!
開槍，瓦西堙I
Come on, pick your feet up.
大家起來
Get on your feet. Prepare to board the train.
起來，準備上火車，快走
This is a military convoy.
這是護送軍隊的列車
No one stays on board but our valiant soldiers.
除了英勇的軍人，所有人都下車
This is a convoy to Stalingrad...
這是護送紅軍前往斯大林格勒的列車
only for the soldiers of the Red Army.
本列車只接載我們的英勇軍人
Autumn, 1942.
1942年秋天
Europe lies crushed beneath the Nazi jackboot.
納粹黨的軍隊橫行歐洲
The German Third Reich I sat the height of its power.
德國勢力達到頂峰
Hitler's armies are charging through the heart of the Soviet Union...
正攻入蘇聯心臟
towards the oilfields of Asia.
向中東的油田進發
One last obstacle remains. A city on the Volga...
他們只剩下一塊絆腳石
where the fate of the world is being decided. Stalingrad.
全球命運全繫於伏爾加河畔一個城市 斯大林格勒
Glorious comrade Stalin...
斯大林同志有令：
has ordered not another step backwards.
絕不後退
The people of the Soviet Union shall be free.
蘇聯人民要爭取自由 決不淪為奴隸
Go forward, comrades. Not a step backwards!
同志們，前進！一步也不能後退
Listen to these letters sent by Russian mothers...
這些信是俄羅斯母親寫給
to their sons on the front.
在前線的兒子，聽聽吧
"Volodya, my child, I know that it's for our motherland-
兒…我知道這是為了祖國
"I know that it's for our motherland that you are giving your life.
你為了祖國獻出自己的生命
"Everyone here knows that you will not fall back.
大家都知道你絕不退縮
"Everyone here is proud of you.
大家都以你為榮
"Your father is dead. Your brothers are dead.
你父親死了，兄弟死了
Avenge us on the hordes of fascists."
你要向法西斯黨討回這份血債
Nobody move! Stay on the boat!
- 誰也不准動！ - 不准離船！
Back from the rails, or we shoot. Shoot the traitors!
射死叛徒！
Come on, come on! Move!
準備上岸！
Come on, comrades, come on!
上岸！
Over here, stretcher!
這邊！分開
The one with the rifle shoots!
有槍的人就開槍
One out of two gets a rifle.
每兩個人一支槍
The one without follows him!
有槍的人走前，沒槍的人隨後
When the one with the rifle gets killed,
有槍的人倒下了…
the one who is following picks up the rifle and shoots!
隨後沒槍的人就檢起槍，開槍
The one with the rifle shoots!
有槍的人就開槍
The one without follows him!
沒槍的人隨後
When the one with the rifle gets killed,
有槍的人倒下了…
the one who is following...
隨後沒槍的人
picks up the rifle and shoots!
就檢起槍，開槍
The one with the rifle shoots!
有槍的人就開槍
This way, now. The one without follows him!
沒槍的人隨後
Soldiers of the glorious Red Army, from now on...
光榮的紅軍軍人…
it is either victory or death!
我們不成功便成仁
Those who retreat will be shot. I need a rifle.
- 退縮者會遭槍斃 - 我需要槍
There will be no mercy For cowards and traitors!
我們決不放過懦夫和叛徒！
It's hopeless, comrades. Get back!
沒希望了，同志們！
Pullback!
撤退！
In the name of the Soviet Union,
奉蘇聯之命…
not a step backwards, or we shoot.
你們不准後退，否則被槍斃！
No retreat! Not a step back!
不准後退半步！
No mercy! Deserters will be shot.
我們不會開恩！逃兵將被殺！
Fire! Shoot the traitors!
開槍！
Cowards will be shot!
槍斃叛徒！
No mercy for cowards!
絕不寬待懦夫！
Russians, surrender. You will see your home again.
俄羅斯人，投降吧！投降就可以重見家園
This is not your war.
這場仗不關你們事
Join your German comrades, They understand your suffering...
加入德軍，他們體恤你們的苦況
and will care more for you than your own officers,
比你們的軍官更關心你們
who are only sending you to your death.
你們的軍官只派你們去送死
The Third Reich Is not your enemy.
第三帝國不是你們的敵人
The enemy is blood thirsty Stalin And his Bolshevik camp,
你們的敵人是嗜血的斯大林與他的黨徒
who have stolen your land, who have deported your father-
他們偷你們的土地 放逐你們的父親
Fire!
開火！
You'll get us caught, comrade Commissar.
政委同志，這樣我們會被發現的
With your permission, comrade Commissar.
政委同志，請讓我來
Which one should I aim at first? You should wait...
應該先射哪一個？
till there's an explosion.
應該先等爆炸才開槍
Do you know how to shoot? A little.
你懂開槍嗎？一點點
Don't shoot. Don't shoot. He's looking at us.
不要開槍，他正看過來！
Thank you, comrade Commissar.
謝謝你，政委同志
Danilov, political officer, second class.
丹尼洛夫，第21步兵團
Twenty-first infantry.
二等政治委員
"Vassili Zaitsev."
瓦西
"On this day, September the 20th, 1942,
1942年9月20日…
"a shepherd boy from the Urals...
一名來自烏拉爾的年輕牧羊人
"arrived in the city of Stalingrad, on the banks of the Volga.
抵達伏爾加河畔的斯大林格勒
"His name is Vassili Zaitsev.
他名叫瓦西
"Like thousands before him, he came to answer comrade Stalin's call.
他是響應斯大林同志的呼喚而來
"Armed with a rifle, he quickly made the fascist invader realize that...
只拿著一支槍…就很快令納粹侵略者明白到…
"from now on he would be punished for every step he took in the motherland;
他們不及早回頭
that from here on, the only way was back."
只有死路一條
What do you think?
你認為怎樣？
I think comrade Commissar's been overgenerous.
我認為政委同志太過獎了
Let me go! Let me go!
放我過去！放我過去！
By order of comrade Stalin, no civilian can leave the city.
斯大林同志有令：市民不准離城
Get back!
回去！
Stand away, or we will open fire.
走開，否則我們開槍！
Stand away!
走開！
Get back!
回去
Get back or we shoot!
回去，否則我們開槍！
Back! Keep back!
回去…
Make way for comrade Stalin 's envoy!
斯大林同志的官員駕到，快讓路
I carried out my orders.
我有執行命令
I sent in all of my boys.
我把小伙子統統送了上戰場
But the Germans engulfed us.
不過，敵我軍力懸殊
They have artillery, aircraft, tanks.
他們有大炮、飛機、坦克…
And me, what did I have? The sacred duty to resist!
- 我們呢？有什麼？ - 我們有神聖的抗戰使命！
I have to report to the boss.
我要向領袖報告
Perhaps you'd prefer to avoid the red tape.
你最好自我了斷
My name is...
我叫…
Nikita Sergeyevich Kruschev.
尼吉達·卓基域治·赫魯曉夫
I've come to take things in hand here.
我來接管這
This city is not Kursk...
本市不是庫斯克
nor is it Kiev, nor Minsk.
不是基輔，也不是明斯克
This city is Stalingrad.
本市是斯大林格勒
Stalingrad!
斯大林…格勒
This city bears the name of the boss.
本市背負著領袖的名字
It's more than a city, it's a symbol.
不僅是個城市，更是個標誌
If the Germans capture this city,
假如德軍佔領了本市
the entire country will collapse.
全國就會瓦解
Now, I want our boys...
現在，我要我們的小伙子
to raise their heads.
抬頭挺胸！
I want them to act like they have balls!
我要他們拿出勇氣來！
I want them to stop shitting their pants!
不准他們再怕得屁滾尿流！
That's your job.
你們是政委
As political officers, I'm counting on you.
激勵士氣是你們的職責
You, what's your suggestion?
你，你有什麼建議？
Shoot all the other generals who have retreated...
把退縮的將軍
and their chiefs of staff too.
參謀長統統槍斃
M-Make some examples.
立下範例
D-D-Deport families of the deserters- Yeah, that's all been done.
- 放逐逃兵的家屬　- 做過了
Give them hope!
給士兵希望
Here, the men's only choice is between German bullets and ours.
他們現在不是死於敵軍就是我軍
But there's another way. The way of courage.
不過，還有另一條路
The way of love of the motherland.
就是勇氣之路、愛國之路
We must publish the army newspaper again.
我們必須再次印發軍報
We must tell magnificent stories. Stories that extol...
報導英勇事跡
sacrifice, bravery.
歌頌報國精神
We must make them believe in the victory.
確立必勝信念
We must give them hope, pride, a desire to fight.
燃點群眾的希望，激發鬥志
Yes, we need to make examples.
是的，我們要立下範例
But examples to follow.
但那是供人學習的範例
What we need... are heroes.
我們需要…英雄
Do you know any heroes around here?
這埵陪^雄？
Yes, comrade, I know one.
有，同志，我認識一個
That's me!
那是我！
"Vassili Zaitsev." That's me!
瓦西堙I那是我！
No, you're not dreaming. It's your name.
你不是在做夢 那正是你的名字！
We made the front page.
我們的文章上了頭版！
They haven't changed a word.
他們一字不改！
Do you have any idea what this means?
你知不知道這有多大意義？
It's not the back page, it's not the second page,
不是尾頁，也不是第二頁
it's the front page. The front page!
是頭版！頭版！
They're going to reprint our article everywhere.
全國各地都會轉載我們的文章
In the Caucasus, in the Crimea, even in the Urals.
高加索、克里米亞 甚至烏拉爾
Tomorrow morning, Stalin himself will be sitting over breakfast,
明早斯大林會一面吃早餐
reading my words, memorizing your name.
一面看我的文字，記得你的名字
We're famous, Vassili. Kruschev loved the article.
我們一舉成名了，瓦西 赫魯曉夫喜歡這篇文章
He's promoted me to the general staff.
他把我升為參謀
And you to sniper division.
而你就調去狙擊隊
Well, that's good. It's very good.
- 好極！ - 十分好！
It's very good. It's great. It's very great!
- 好得很！ - 好極了
It's great! For us because we did it together.
你我合作的成果
Together!
合作
Although I did all the hard work. oh, yeah?
- 困難的部分都由我做了 - 是嗎？
You're very lucky I can't fight back. Why's that?
- 你走運，我不能打你 - 為什麼？
Because Kruschev told me to make sure nothing happens to you.
赫魯曉夫要我保障你安全
You're too important. I'm too valuable.
- 你現在很重要 - 我很有價值
Yes, careful of my- careful of my glasses, please. They're new.
小心我的眼鏡
Sorry, sir.
對不起
I'm famous! We're famous! I'm famous! I'm famous!
我成名了！我們成名了！
Vassili, the young shepherd from the Urals,
來自烏拉爾的瓦西
killed his 12th German officer today.
今天殺了第12名德軍！
He used to hunt wolves, Now he shoots fascists.
他從前殺狼，現在殺法西斯分子
Today, Vassili Zaitsev shot his 23rd German officer.
瓦西堣竣拲了第23名德軍！
He is an example to us all.
瓦西埵A殺了一名上校
Vassili shot his 32ndGerman officer.
瓦西堣竣拲了第32名德軍！
Count only the Germans you have killed.
別算日子，只算殺了幾個德軍
Today, Vassili Zaitsev- Here is the evidence-
瓦西堣竣拲了第46名德軍！
11 dog tags retrieved by sniper Vassili Zaitsev.
瓦西堣T日內取得十一個軍牌
More and more men and women, fighters from all branches of our armed forces,
不分男女，越來越多…
join the sniper division and learn the skills of Vassili Zaitsev.
志願加入狙擊隊…向瓦西媥Е
I am a stone.
我是塊石頭
I breathe slowly.
我放輕呼吸
I aim at the eye.
我瞄準眼睛
So it is you,
你就是…
the great Vassili Zaitsev.
大名鼎鼎的瓦西堙I
My mother makes potatoes with bacon. Sounds good.
- 我媽媽燒得一手頂級煙肉薯仔 - 聽來不錯
When she sees you, she won't believe her eyes.
她見到你，不知道會多高興呢
How many today? Only two.
- 今天殺了幾個？ - 只有兩個
And the last one, why didn't you shoot him?
最後那個為什麼不殺？
He was only a foot soldier. Wasn't worth giving away my position.
他只是個步兵 不值得為了他而暴露我的位置
Bless you.
願上帝保佑你
We know how much we owe you.
我們欠你很多
We pray for you every day.
我們每天都為你禱告
Every evening, we listen to them talk about you on Radio Moscow.
我們每晚都聽電台對你的報導
Thanks. You've certainly managed well down here.
謝謝 你們這地下室相當不錯
My parents used to store furniture down here before the war.
戰前我父母在這埵s放傢私
Sacha, drop that right now.
沙查！把槍放下！
It's loaded.
裝了子彈的
This way, comrade Commissar.
政委同志，這邊
Thank you, comrade.
謝謝你，同志
Good evening.
各位好
Comrade Zaitsev?
瓦西埵P志
My God, where does all this mail come from?
好多信，從哪堭H來的？
From all over the country, Mrs. Filipov, from all over.
全國各地都有
This one's from the workers of the Kouzbass.
庫茲巴斯的礦工來信說…
They want to name their mine after Vassili.
打算把礦場命名為瓦西媊q場
Right, let's start with the miners.
先答覆礦工的信吧
Come on, let's get to work.
開始吧
Dear comrades from the Kouzbass,
庫茲巴斯的同志，你們好
Kouzbass. I thank you for your letter of praise.
多謝你們的稱讚
Praise? R-A-I-S-E.
- 「稱讚」怎樣串？ - PRAISE
And... I hope that I can live up...
希望我能
to your expectations A-T-I-O-N-S.
不負所望
Expectations.
不負所望…
You're interested in German literature, Mrs. Filipov?
費太太，你對德國文學有興趣？
It's all right, it's our neighbor.
不要緊，她是鄰居
Right, where were we? Tania, we have guests.
- 寫到哪堙H - 坦妮亞，我們有客人
Your offer to name-
你提議命名…
I...
你好
I-I recognize you.
你好…我認得你…
He's Vassili Zaitsev.
他是瓦西堙I
I saw your picture in the paper.
我在報紙上看過你的照片
Thank you For everything you're doing.
感謝你所做的一切
And this is his friend, Commissar... Danilov.
這位是他朋友，政委…丹尼洛夫
Danilov.
丹尼洛夫
Tania is like a daughter to me.
我把坦妮亞當作親生女
She used to take care of Sacha when I worked at the factory.
我在工廠幹活時，沙查由她照顧
She even taught him German. All these books are hers.
她甚至教沙查德語 這些書都是她的
Oh, they're yours? She studied German at the university.
- 是你的？ - 她在大學讀德文
Which university? Moscow.
- 哪間大學？ - 莫斯科大學
Moscow. Moscow.
莫斯科
Shouldn't we, uh-
好不好…
Yes, let's continue.
好，繼續回信
Your offer to name Your mine after me...
你提議把礦場命名為瓦西媊q場
is... a great honor.
我深感榮幸
Yes, I know. Honor.
- HON… - 我懂得拼「榮幸」
Very good.
很好
Shouldn't we make the point that I'm not the only one fighting?
應不應該…強調不只我一個人在作戰？
That...That's excellent...excellent idea, Vassili.
好主意
We can take it even further though. Oh.
可以在這點上加以發揮
We can take it further.
對，加以發揮
Your battle for The production of coal...
你們為產煤而奮鬥…
is as worthy as mine.
所作出的貢獻一樣重要
There's no "K" in coal.
「煤」沒有K字
Just-just one "L."
只有一個「L」，對了
Oh, tell me if I'm going too fast.
我是不是說得太快？
No, you're not going too fast. You sure?
- 你說得不太快 - 真的嗎？
Why don't you get some rest? These letters can wait until tomorrow.
你們休息一會吧 信明天再寫也不遲
We should carry on. We're not tired.
我們要繼續寫 我們不累，
Thank you, Mrs. Filipov. These people...
謝謝關心，費太太
took the trouble to write to us.
這些人一番熱誠寫信來
Tomorrow, we may not be around to write back.
我們明天未必有機會回復
Major Konig, Herr General.
將軍，高寧少校來了
I was expecting someone...
我早知道柏林會派人來
Certainly not someone so prestigious.
但料不到會是你這樣顯赫的人
I imagine you have your reasons...
你肯插手這棘手的事，
for getting yourself involved in this hellish situation.
必有原因
My army is not designed For this kind of fighting.
我軍不習慣這種作戰方式
Yesterday, yet again, I had to promote...
昨天我要提升25個沙展
25 sergeants to replace the officers shot down by their sharpshooters.
代替那些死於狙擊手槍下的軍官
Those snipers are demoralizing my people.
那些狙擊手打擊了我們的士氣
This city is no more than...
這個城市
a heap of ruins.
同廢墟差不多
But the fuehrer's persisting.
不過，首領還要窮追猛打
He has made it a personal matter between Stalin and himself.
借此解決他和斯大林的私人恩怨
We should trust the fuehrer's instinct.
我們應該信賴首領的直覺
He always managed to lead us to victory.
他一向帶領我們取得勝利
We shall be back home For Christmas.
我們可以回家度聖誕
How are you going to go about finding this young Russian?
你打算怎樣找這年輕的俄國人？
I'll fix it so that he's the one who finds me.
我會安排好，讓他來找我
Vassili. Vassili.
瓦西
Come on, time to get up. What?
- 該起床了 - 什麼？
They have a problem in the department store sector. They need us. Come on.
百貨公司那埵陶繚苤A需要幫忙
Look, Vassili, he's hiding in the department store. Over there.
那狙擊手躲在百貨公司堶
So far this morning,
他今早
he's knocked off five officers, plus two machine gunners.
射死了五個軍官和兩個機關鎗手
Look, third floor, fourth window from the left.
看！三樓左邊第四個窗口
Fourth window from the left.
左邊第四個窗口
See him?
看到他嗎？
Yeah, I see him.
看到
There, you got him!
射中了！
Great shot.
好槍法！
Let's go get his dog tag.
去拿他的軍牌吧
Good-bye, comrade Commissar.
再見，政委同志
Thank you for your hospitality, Mrs. Filipov.
感謝你的款待，費太太
You can borrow whatever you like.
隨便借閱好了
I'm not sure what they would say to me at headquarters...
捧著一堆哥德、雪萊作品回去…
if I came back with an armful of Goethe and Schiller.
總部的人不知道會怎樣說
There's some Marx too.
我也有馬克思的作品
You were assigned to civil defense at the 12th district?
你被調去第12區做民兵
No, I volunteered.
不，我是志願的
It's such a coincidence meeting you like this.
真巧，赫魯曉夫同志…
Comrade Kruschev was telling me just yesterday...
昨天才對我說…
how desperately we're in need of operators who speak German.
我們極需要會德語的通訊員
I can't. Our militia's responsible for all the people in this neighbourhood.
不可以 我們的部隊負責本區的安全
We're already desperately short of men.
人手已經很短缺
We'll give you a dozen soldiers for every one that speaks German.
我們願意用十二個士兵交換你
I'd rather stay and fight.
我寧願留下來作戰
Serving at headquarters is fighting. You'd be far more useful there.
服務總部也是作戰，你會更有用
You stay here. You cover us.
你留下來，掩護我們
All right. We go.
好 我們去了
Take care.
保重
Ludmilla, come on.
陸米拉，來
Check the stairway.
查看樓梯！
It's a trap.
這是個圈套
I know.
我知道
Move back.
退回去！
He's still here.
他還在這
They're coming straight for us! Ludmilla,
他們正轟炸過來！
stay where you are, he's over there somewhere.
不要動 他還在附近埋伏
We have to get out of here!
我們要離開這堙I
We have to get out of here! Just stay where you are!
- 不走不行！- 不要動！
What are we gonna do?
怎麼辦？
Ludmilla, stay where you are!
留在原地別動！
Fuck this, I'm going.
我不管！我要走了
Ludmilla, no!
陸米拉，不要走！
What does this mean?
上面寫的是什麼？
"The little shepherd from the Urals receives a new sniper's rifle,
瓦西媕繺o新的狙擊槍
"a Mosin-Nagant 7.62, with its 3.5-Power P.U. Telescope.
莫納7.62型，配備3.5倍望遠鏡
Pride of precision of Soviet production."
蘇聯最得意的精良武器
I've seen that rifle close up. Have you?
- 我親眼見過 - 是嗎？
I've even touched it. I know him well, Vassili Zaitsev.
甚至摸過 我跟瓦西堳僂籅滿K
Ludmilla and Anton were killed today, and it was my fault.
陸米拉和安東今天死了 都是我的錯
No, I'm sure that's not true.
我肯定這不是事實
There was a German sniper. I walked them right into his trap.
那埵陪蚍w軍狙擊手 我帶他們中了他的圈套
What else can you tell me? He didn't relocate.
- 你還知道什麼？ - 他沒有轉移陣地
A sniper who doesn't relocate isn't normal.
狙擊手不轉移陣地是不合常規的
He was very good. It wasn't just his shooting, it was his instinct.
他很厲害 不僅槍法好，而且有很準的直覺
He was a step ahead of me all the time.
他的行動往往比我早一步
That's because he knows everything about you.
那是因為他對你瞭如指掌
His name is Konig, Major Konig.
他叫高寧，高寧少校
They've sent him here to ki-
德軍派他來
to find you.
是為了殺…找你
At first we weren't sure if the information was reliable.
我們起初不知道線報是否可靠
It seems he's come all the way from Berlin to stop you.
他似乎專程從柏林來殺你
You've caused them so many sleepless nights, they sent their top marksman.
你令他們寢食難安，他們要你死
What do we know about him? He's a major in the Wehrmacht.
- 他是什麼來頭？ - 他是德軍的少校
He's director of their sniper school in Zossen.
在索申擔任狙擊訓練所所長
Koulikov studied under him at Zossen before the war.
戰前，科堶穭珚罋L他學習
He knows all his tricks. From now on, he'll go with you everywhere.
很清楚他的伎倆 由現在起，你去哪堙A他去哪
A nobleman from Bavaria who hunts deer...
來自巴伐利亞的獵鹿貴族
against a shepherd boy from the Urals who poaches wolves.
跟來自烏拉爾的殺狼小子對決
It's more than a confrontation between two nations.
這不僅是兩國之戰
It's the essence of class struggle.
也標誌著階級鬥爭
I'm glad you're so happy.
很高興你這樣興奮
He had all the advantages. Next time you'll be even.
他佔盡上風 下次你會打平
No one shoots like you, Vassili.
你的槍法所向無敵
She's been transferred.
她被調職了
I'll see if they're ready for you next door.
我去看看隔壁準備好了沒有
Hello. You look smart in your new uniform.
你好 你穿上新制服好英俊
Make sure they don't take it back once you've finished.
結束後別交還
Yeah, they probably will.
可能要交還
I've heard the rumor about the German, and I wanted to wish you luck.
我聽過那德國人的事 祝你好運
Thank you. I'll need it.
謝謝，我現在很需要運氣
From what comrade Danilov tells me, you're going to win.
丹尼洛夫同志說…你穩操勝券
It's time.
時間到了！
Vassili! Vassili! Come to my arms.
瓦西堙K這邊！讓我擁抱
Look in my direction.
望過來，瓦西
Put your cap back on, you look more heroic.
戴著帽吧，這樣更似英雄
This way, comrade Zaitsev. I love this little fellow.
這邊，瓦西埵P志 這小伙子甚得我心！
Vassili, is it true that you volunteered for the front?
瓦西堙A你真的自願上前線？
How old are you, Vassili?
你幾歲？
Do you know what this duel means for our country?
你知道這對國家有多大意義嗎？
Is it true you killed your first wolf when you were five?
你是不是五歲就殺狼？
Are you proud to be challenged By the best sharpshooter in Germany?
德國派神槍手對付你，你驕傲嗎
The Germans are starting to shit their pants.
這表示德國鬼開始怕我們了
Go on, my boy, tell us how you're going to deal with him.
對他們講你怎樣對付他吧
Or rather, no. Tell it to the boss. One more question, please.
還是別對他們講 對領袖講吧！
He likes good hunting stories.
他喜歡聽追獵的故事
Look at him with pride,
挺起胸膛看著他
because he's looking at you.
因為他正看著你
The whole country is looking at you.
全國正看著你
Forgive me, forgive me, Grandfather.
原諒我吧，爺爺
So, it's not the wolf that chooses the hunting ground...
狩獵場不是由狼決定
but the hunter.
是由獵人決定的
But I'm sure your grandfather taught you that.
你爺爺必定教過你
Except in this case,
不過，
I'm the game.
今次我是獵物
However, today what we're going to do...
我們要引狼出窖
is lure the wolf out of his lair...
把狼引到我們要狼到的地方
You're the one whose life is valuable. You go first.
你的命值錢，你先跳
No, no. We take it in turns. Next time is your turn to go first,
不，我們輪流先跳 下次，輪到你先跳
and then it's you, Volodya.
然後輪到你，伏洛迪亞
Son of a bitch!
混蛋
These are new pants. I just took them off a captain from the 251st yesterday.
這是新的褲子 我昨天才從一名隊長身上脫下來
Sixteen months I spent in Germany at the school in Zossen.
我在德國的索申住了16個月
Of course, those were the days when we were friends with the Krauts, :
當然那時我們還沒跟德國佬交惡
When our Joseph and their Adolph...
我們的斯大林跟他們的希特勒
were walking hand in hand.
當時還在稱兄道弟
From here to the wire, 160meters, right?
這娷鷞q線有160米吧？
One hundred and fifty-five.
155…
Whatever. That'll make 'em Send out a repair guy.
無所謂這一來，他們要派人來修理
Let's relocate.
轉移陣地吧
Hey, Volodya!
伏洛迪亞！
After the Germans invaded us,
德國侵略我們之後…
it wasn't the same atmosphere anymore.
氣氛完全不同了
Threw my ass in prison.
我無辜給人抓去坐牢
What were you doing in Germany, huh?
「你去德國做什麼？」
Excuse me, says I, but it was comrade Stalin who sent me there.
我答：抱歉，斯大林同志派我去
Don't bring our glorious leader into your treachery.
不要詆毀我們偉大的領袖
Confess, spy bastard! Confess.
認罪吧，奸細
And bang! Bang, bang, bang!
跟著…
Well, there wasn't a sickle, but there was a hammer.
他們拿出的不是鐮刀，是鐵錘
And bang. Knocked out all my teeth.
跟著…把我的牙統統敲掉
That's right, boy. Have no illusions.
對了，小伙子，不要心存幻想
That's the land of socialism and universal bliss for you.
這就是社會主義的幸福境界
Hey! It's your repair guy.
維修的人來了！
I got him.
我瞄準了
It's about soup time, isn't it?
該喝湯了吧？
I'm going.
我去拿
Well, get a move on, Volodya,
那還不去？伏洛迪亞
and try not to spill it all on your way back, you Marxist bastard.
不要倒洩，你這馬克思混蛋
The enemy sniper activity reported during the past 24 hours, Herr Major.
這是過去一天敵軍的狙擊記錄
Two sentries shot in the train station sector.
火車站的兩名哨兵
One artillery observer in the Northern sector.
北區一名大炮觀察員
One lieutenant from the 24th Panzer division in the factory sector.
工廠區第24裝甲部隊一名少尉
Three telephone repairmen in the workers' housing sector.
工人宿舍三名通訊工兵
They also tell me we have just taken a prisoner who may interest you.
我們抓到戰俘，你或者會想盤問
I hope he's still able to speak.
希望他還能夠答話吧
Excuse me, sir?
什麼？少校
Nothing. Thank you.
沒什麼，謝謝
So, tell us, Volodya,
伏洛迪亞，
which building is he in?
他在哪幢樓內？
There is no way I know that.
我不可能知道
He moves around all the time.
他不斷走來走去
He jumps from one to the next.
從一幢樓跳去另一幢
On which floor?
在哪一層？
I don't know.
不知道
We'll see about that.
我們很快會知道
Undress him.
把他的衣服脫掉
Put him in one of our uniforms.
給他穿上我們的軍服
You see, they are stubborn.
看，他們多頑固
That's the good thing about the Germans.
這是德國人的優點
Man, you got to admit when they get an idea in their heads-
你得承認，假如他們打定主意…
Right.
好
Let's see if our customer has arrived.
看看顧客來了沒有
Are you ready?
準備好了嗎
And now our famous shepherd from the Urals,
高寧少校眼中的白癡
who Major Konig thinks is an idiot,
我們有名的烏拉爾牧羊人
gets up to make sure he has hit his target.
站了起來，看看自己射中了沒有
Major Konig sees him.
高寧少校看到他
Aims for his helmet.
瞄準他的頭盔…
Fires.
開槍
Reveals his position And is shot in turn.
他暴露了自己的位置 反而被射死了
Except... Major Konig doesn't fire...
可是…高寧少校並沒有開槍
because Major Konig isn't there.
因為高寧少校並不在
Koulikov!
科堶穭
Don't you think that was strange, that last one?
你不覺得剛才很奇怪嗎？
They sent him out to get shot like the others.
他們明知出來就要被射死
It's not natural.
卻依然派人出來，
Not without artillery, without trying to cover him.
而且不掩護他 這很不尋常
Oh, no, I'm the one who was stupid.
我才是蠢的那個
They don't give a shit about telephone guys.
他們才不在乎通訊兵的死活
I mean, it's like us with the Ukrainians.
就像我們對待烏克蘭人一樣
They'd never bother a major over a few dead grunts.
死幾個烏克蘭佬，我們眉也不皺
Tomorrow, we'll kill us some generals.
我們明天殺幾個將軍吧
Whose turn is it?
輪到誰？
Mine, I think.
似乎輪到我
Oh, you're such a cheater!
騙人！
You can't fool Papa Koulikov.
想騙科堶穭狳叔？妄想
No, no, no, no, no, no, no, it's my turn to go first.
輪到我先跳
And it's your turn to get a hole in your britches.
輪到你的褲子被射穿
To victory.
祝我們勝利！
This sniper business has been dragging on too long.
狙擊決鬥的事拖得太久了
What's that little fellow of yours up to?
你那小子有什麼進展？
He's probing, comrade Kruschev.
他在試探，赫魯曉夫同志
He's testing the Germans for weaknesses.
要找出那德國人的弱點
He's meticulous in his preparation.
他很小心的準備
Vodka... is a luxury we have.
伏特加這種奢侈品，我們有
Caviar is a luxury we have.
魚子醬這種奢侈品，我們有
Time is not.
時間，我們沒有
He's aware of that comrade Kruschev. We both are.
這點他明白，我倆都明白
I assure you he will succeed.
我保證他會成功
Good.
好
It seems your destinies are entwined.
你倆的命運息息相關
They're keeping you busy.
你相當忙
I picked this up in the kitchen.
我在廚房撿來
It's from the reception the other day. I thought Mrs. Filipov might like it.
這是前幾天的招待會剩下來的 我想費太太會喜歡
Um, she will be thrilled. That's very sweet of you.
她會很高興，你真好
There's plenty more if you're hungry.
你餓的話，還有很多
You'e Jewish, aren't you?
你是猶太教的吧？
There's nothing in our religion that says you can't eat sturgeon.
我們的宗教並不禁止吃鱘魚
My father had a premonition all this would happen.
我爸爸早已預感到這會發生
You mean the war?
你指預感到戰事？
He understood that the hatred of the jews ran deep.
他知道大家一向都仇恨猶太人
He was saving up to buy some land in Palestine.
他在儲蓄，打算到巴勒斯坦買地
He said it was the only land we truly belonged in;
他說我們的國土只有巴勒斯坦
the only land we had a duty to defend.
我們要保衛的只有巴勒斯坦
He insisted learn to use a rifle.
他一定要我學開槍
I learned to shoot.
於是我學會了開槍
I know that in times of war, personal feelings should be put aside, but...
我知道打仗時個人感情要放在一旁
I have a favor to ask you.
但我想請你幫忙
Of course. Anything you want.
沒問題，儘管說
I want to be reassigned.
我想調職
What's happened, Tania?
坦妮亞，怎麼了？
He shot him.
他射死了科堶穭
He shot him even though he jumped first.
儘管先跳過去的是科堶穭
Shot him on the run.
他跳躍時被殺死
It was an impossible shot.
神乎其技，
I've never seen anything like it.
我沒見過人這樣厲害
You've promised people a victory I can't deliver.
你作出的勝利承諾，我沒法兌現
I don't stand a chance against this man.
我不是他的對手，毫無勝算
You mustn't talk like that, Vassili.
你不可以這樣說
What if I told you we found a way to track his movements?
我們有辦法追蹤到他的行動
We've got someone, Vassili.
我們有探子
Someone close to him passing us information.
那探子很接近他
Next time you will be one step ahead of him.
下次你的行動會比他早一步
I promise.
我保證
Now I have a favor to ask.
現在我想請你幫個忙
From me?
我幫你忙？
It's about Tania.
關於坦妮亞的
Come in.
進來
He doesn't even know you exist.
他甚至不知道你存在…
But at that moment, you are closer to him than anyone else on earth.
但那一刻，你比任何人更接近他
You see his face through the sight.
你通過瞄準器清楚看到他的臉
You see whether he shaved that morning or not.
看得出他早上有沒有剃鬚…
You can see whether he's married by whether he has a wedding ring on.
有沒有戴戒指，有沒有家室
It's not like...
你要將狙擊的…
just firing at a distant shape, not just a uniform.
不是死物，也不是僅僅一套軍服
It's a man's face.
而是人的臉
Those faces don't go away.
那些臉孔不會消失
They come back and they just- they get replaced by more faces.
會在你的腦海堹B現 一張張新的臉孔會添上去
Did Danilov ask you to tell me this?
丹尼洛夫叫你來說這一番話？
He likes you very much. I think he'd try anything to change your mind.
他喜歡你，想盡力改變你的主意
Did he tell you why I asked for the transfer?
他有沒有說我為什麼想調職？
No.
沒有
This morning, a list arrived at headquarters.
今早總部接到一份名單
It was a list of civilians who'd been...
是一批三個星期前…
rounded up and sent to Germany in a convoy...
從斯大林格勒
that left Stalingrad three weeks ago.
押解去德國的平民
My parents were amongst them.
我父母當時身在其中
After 30 kilometers, the German soldiers...
火車駛了30公里
stopped the train and forced everyone out.
停下來，德軍把所有人趕下車
In the middle of a bridge, they bound them together,
在橋中央，德軍把大家綁起來
two by two.
綁成一對對
Mothers with daughters.
母與女、
Husbands and wives.
夫與妻
They... lined them up against the railing,
德軍叫那些人在橋邊排隊
and then they fired a single shot at each pair...
然後每一對射一槍
to save bullets.
以節省子彈
It worked.
這方法奏效
The bodies of the ones who died dragged the others under the water.
在世的人跳海，隨被射死的人去
I know they died together.
我知道他們死在一起
They never would have let themselves be separated.
他們決不願意分開
That's Koulikov's rifle. It's a good... rifle.
這是科堶穭猁漕B槍，性能很好
Thank you.
謝謝
I know how he leaves the shelter.
我知道他怎樣離開防空洞
He goes through the tractor factory.
他穿過拖拉機廠
The tractor factory is big.
拖拉機廠很大的
I know exactly where. He crawls through a gutter,
我清楚知道他走的路徑 他沿著大桶鐵格下的溝渠…
under a grate where the vats are,
一直往前爬
then he goes out from the workshop.
然後從工場走出來
In between the two, there's a place where he's in the open.
其中有一段路沒有掩護
It's under a long, iron foot walk.
那一段路在鐵長廊之下
Good luck, comrade.
祝你好運，同志
I know exactly where he's waiting for me.
我知道他會在哪媯平唭
He'll be on the foot walk over the gutter.
在溝渠上的鐵長廊
We'll take him out from behind.
我們從後面襲擊他
We'll get to the other end of the workshop through these pipes.
我們沿著喉管，走去工場另一邊
Follow me.
跟我來！
You go that way. I'll go around this way.
你從那邊去 我從這邊繞過去
Okay?
好的
Shit!
糟糕！
Sergei, you should go back.
不要緊 你應該回去
No, I'll be all right. Go back.
不 我不會有事
No, you go!
不，回去！
Keep your legs in.
把腿縮進去
Come on. Come on. Come on.
來吧
Comrade Stalin is asking for one last effort!
斯大林同志要你們拼盡全力
The fate of the motherland is at risk!
祖國的命運危在旦夕
The fate of all those you love and cherish!
你們所珍愛的人也危在旦夕
It's for them that we fight today.
我們今天要為他們奮戰
Listen to me, Tania. The Germans are throwing everything at us.
聽我勸吧，坦妮亞 德國向我們發動大舉攻擊
If they're lucky, one in ten of these soldiers will come back alive.
十個士兵中只有一個能活著回來
You're highly educated. You know languages.
你受過高等教育，通曉外語
Every intercept you translate saves hundreds of lives.
你截聽、解讀情報
Every message you decode kills thousands of theirs.
能拯救許多同胞，殺掉許多敵人
You have a duty to survive.
你有責任活下去
Vassili was born to fire a gun. It's what he knows.
瓦西媥晡禷}槍，是天生的槍手
You and I were born for a different purpose.
你我卻另有作用
If Vassili were here, he would tell you the same thing.
瓦西堣]會對你說同一番話
Where is he? Where is Vassili?
他在哪堙H瓦西埵b哪堙H
Keep your head down.
把頭伏下
Tell me where he is. Stay into that pipe, Tania.
- 告訴我槍手在哪 - 躲在管內，
Stay in. Stay in! Get your head in!
不要出來，把頭縮起
Slow down.
慢慢來
Don't shoot.
不要開槍
He's over there.
他在那
Do you see the pillar in front of you?
見到你前面的柱子嗎？
I need you to move round behind it.
我要你到柱子的後面去
Go.
去吧
Tania, I need you to find a large piece of glass.
我要你找一大塊玻璃
Piece of glass.
一塊玻璃？
Do you see the kiln...
我後面工廠的左邊…
behind me to the left of the factory?
有座窖，看得見嗎？
Yes? I can't hear you.
看不看得見？我聽不到
Yes. Yes.
- 看見 - 看見
Do you see...
看見兩扇百葉窗嗎？
Yes. Do you see the one...
- 看見 - 看不看得見…
with a broken slat?
破了百葉板的那一扇？
Yes.
看見
This is what I want you to do.
這就是我要你做的事
Are you ready? Yes.
- 準備好了嗎？ - 準備好了
Hello, Sacha.
你好，沙查
He was right where you said he'd be.
你說中了他出現的地方
Nearly there.
差不多說中
He's very clever.
他很聰明
Tell me about him.
說說他的事來聽
Why was it his grandfather taught him how to shoot and not his father?
為何不是爸爸而是爺爺教他開槍
His father's dead. His mother too.
他爸爸死了，媽媽也死了
Does he talk about his father?
他有沒有提起爸爸？
No. He didn't know him.
不提，他不認識爸爸
Did he go to school?
他有上過學嗎？
He knows how to write. He answers lots of letters.
他懂得寫字，復很多信
Hmm. Is it girls who write to him?
女孩的信？
Everyone writes to him.
人人都寫信給他
Is there a girl he loves in his village?
他在家鄉有沒有喜歡的女孩？
Not in his village, here. Does she love him?
不是在家鄉，在這 那女孩喜歡他嗎？
Yes, because he's handsome.
喜歡，因為他英俊
Because he's brave and she's very beautiful.
因為他勇敢，那女孩很漂亮
I know her well. She's from my neighbour hood.
我跟她很熟，她是我鄰居
She went to the university. They're handsome together.
她上過大學
Later, the two of them will get married.
他們很登對，將來會結婚
At least, I think so.
起碼我認為是這樣
And you, Sacha,
而你呢？沙查…
why are you helping the Germans?
你為什麼幫德國人？
Because they're stronger. Because they're going to win the war.
因為德國人比較強，會打勝仗
And because you like chocolate, huh?
也因為你愛吃朱古力
All these people here know they're gonna die.
這些人知道自己活不久
So each night when they make it back,
晚上能夠活著回來…
it's a bonus.
算是賺了一天
Excuse me.
對不起
So, every cup of tea,
於是，每一杯茶…
every cigarette...
每一根香煙…
becomes a little celebration.
都成了小小的慶祝
Because for a lot of us, it maybe our last night.
因為這可能是我們的最後一晚
It's just something you have to accept here.
你在這兒要接受這事實
Everyone has their time.
人難免一死
In the forest, the wolf lives for three years,
在森林堙A狼只活三年
the donkey for nine.
驢則活九年
So, that's-that's got to be a proverb from the Urals.
對不起，這必定是以訛傳訛
It makes no sense to me whatsoever.
我認為沒有道理
The donkey lives longer because he's more useful.
驢比較長命，因為它比較有用
Makes absolute sense.
這絕對有道理
There aren't any donkeys in the forest.
森林堶埵備j？
You made it up.
你虛構出來的
So... I'm a donkey?
那麼…我是頭驢嗎？
People like you and Danilov...
你和丹尼洛夫這種人得活下來
People who have read books, had an education.
你們讀過書，受過教育
We'll need you when the war is over.
戰後重建，需要你們
And if you survive?
假如你能活下來呢？
What will the useless Vassili Zaitsev do then?
「無用」的瓦西媟|做什麼？
I wanna work in a factory.
我想在工廠幹活
My granddad took me to a factory once.
爺爺帶過我進工廠一次
There was this man there, high up on a-
高處的鐵走廊上…
on a foot walk.
站著一個人
He wasn't wearing blue like the others.
他與眾不同，不穿藍工作服
The people he was supervising didn't understand what they were doing.
他手下的工人都不明白自己做什麼
But for him, for him up there,
不過…他高高在上
it was simple; it was clear.
一切瞭如指掌
And I thought, "One day, I could be that man."
我希望自己有朝一日能成為那個人
Sad to have a dream you know won't happen.
擁有不能實現的夢想，真難過
Why shouldn't it?
為什麼不可能實現？
You'll outlive us all.
你會長命百歲
You'll be the oldest donkey in the forest.
你會成為森林堻怞悛瘋j
"150 meters stand between the Germans and the Volga.
德軍離伏爾加河有150米
"Today the whole world is watching these 150meters.
這舉世矚目的150米…
They are what makes Stalingrad..."
使斯大林格勒成為…
the capitol...
戰爭的…
of the war.
首都
Your friend, Tania...
你的朋友坦妮亞…
have you see her?
你有沒有見過她？
She stays over there now, with the snipers.
她跟狙擊隊的人在一起
Tell the major we're sending in all of our sharpshooters...
告訴少校
to support the attack on the factory.
所有狙擊手會進攻工廠
Tell him Vassili will be there.
瓦西堣]會參與
I need to talk to you. Sure.
- 我要跟你談談 - 好
Danilov. Hmm?
丹尼洛夫
You have to stop writing about me.
別再寫我了
I'm not gonna get him because I'm not good enough.
我根本不是他對手
Sooner or later, he's gonna find me, he's gonna kill me.
他遲早會找到我，會殺掉我
I've warned you before not to talk like this.
我警告過你，不准說喪氣話
This time it's different.
今次不同
You've built me up...
你把我塑造成一個
and up into someone I'm not.
我做不來的人
I can't carry that weight anymore. I wanna fight.
我再也挑不起這重擔，我想作戰
I want to fight just as a regular soldier.
像普通士兵那樣作戰
I understand.
我明白
The thing is, you're not a regular soldier. You're extraordinary.
但你不是普通士兵，你很出色
No, I'm what you've made me.
那只是你編造出來
Nothing more.
僅此而已
Why are you telling me this now?
為什麼現在說這番話？
Hmm? What's happened?
發生了什麼事？
What's changed?
有什麼改變了？
Did you speak to Tania for me?
你有沒有替我勸勸坦妮亞？
Yes. Well...
有
will she reconsider?
她肯回心轉意嗎？
I don't know.
不知道
She should. She'll be much safer. She should, you know that.
為了安全，她應該回心轉意
Yeah. It'll be easier to get her reassigned.
是的 她調職比你容易
The Germans are preparing another offensive in the city center.
德軍準備再進攻市中心
The propaganda battle is crucial for morale. We need you more than ever.
我們很需要利用你去激勵軍心
Sacha. Hold on. Sacha!
沙查！
Tell him what you know, Sacha. Hello, Sacha.
把你的消息告訴他 沙查，你好
There was dust on the major's boots.
少校的軍靴沾了塵
Sacha has the major convinced he's gone over to the other side.
少校以為沙查投靠了敵方
I don't need to tell you the risk she's taking.
不用我說，你也知他要冒多大險
The dust was yellow. There's only one place where there's dust like that-
塵是黃色的
in the back of the chemical factory, a big heap on the tracks.
全市只有化工廠後面的小徑旁有一大堆黃塵
Well done.
幹得好
Sacha...
沙查
wait for me outside then.
到外面等我
Danilov, Hmm?
丹尼洛夫
You had no right to use him.
你無權利用他
No, no, I didn't use him, Vassili.
我沒有利用他
He did it of his own accord.
他是自願的
You know why?
你知道原因嗎？
Because he believes in you!
因為他信任你
Tomorrow morning, we're going to take back the chemical factory.
明早我們就會收復化工廠
Sacha's informed the major you'll be there,
沙查通知了少校你會去
so now you know where you have to wait for him.
你知道應該在哪堮I伏他
In the middle of an assault. I'm following orders.
在突擊途中 我奉命行事
I suggest you do the same.
建議你也一樣
Now, I'm aware of the risks.
我知道要冒險
You'll be fine.
你會沒事的
Comrade.
同志
That's the Germans up there.
那邊現在是德軍
And yesterday was the Russians.
昨天是俄軍的
We're not very far now.
我們快到了
Sacha...
沙查
you're playing a very dangerous game.
你在玩很危險的遊戲
I want you to win.
我想你打勝仗
See there? Keep going along the river.
看到嗎？沿著河一直走去
It's safe... for a while.
那堳雃w全…暫時
He's dead. We found this on his corpse.
他死了 我們在他屍體上找到的
Your reason for being here has ceased to exist.
你再沒必要留下來
Pardon me, Herr General,
對不起，將軍…
but I do not believe-
但我不相信…
There is a plane bound for Berlin tomorrow evening.
明晚有飛機往柏林
You will be on it.
你要上機
Until then, I must ask you for your dog tags.
登機前，你必須交出軍牌來
Imagine how Russian propaganda would profit from your death.
萬一你死掉，俄軍就會趁機宣傳
If you fall, you will fall unknown.
你死，就要死得無聲無息
You've already had a near miss.
你曾經差點沒命
Also please take this War Merit Cross.
另外，請收下這十字戰勳
It was awarded posthumously...
是追頒給
to a lieutenant of the 116th Infantry Division...
第116步兵師一名上尉
who fell here during the first days of the battle.
開戰不久，他在這堿偽禤蝓
He was my son.
他是我的兒子
If the landing is captured, everything's lost!
碼頭一失守，萬事俱休！
Come here.
過來！
What did I tell you?
我警告過你
You've been playing your fiddle too much!
你玩得太多花樣！
If it's confirmed that he's dead, we're sunk!
假如證實他歸西，我們就會完蛋
Well, you'll sunk. It isn't true.
- 你會完蛋！ - 這不是真的
It was intercepted from their staff headquarters.
他們內部通訊說他已經死了
What do they have to do, dangle his body in front of our men?
難道要他們把屍體吊起你才信？
They're lying.
他們在說謊
That's good. Very good.
好，很好
Write it, then. "Vassili Zaitsev is not dead.
這樣寫吧：瓦西堥癡S有死
"This is what he had for breakfast this morning.
今早他吃這些早餐
This is a picture of him reading today's newspaper."You're the poet".
這是他今天讀報的照片 隨便作吧
What?
什麼？
You won't give up the riverbank!
不准棄守河畔！
I don't care if you'll lost half your men!
已經死掉一半士兵？我不管！
Lose the other half, or lose yourself!
繼續防守，不然就是你自己死掉
Is he back?
他回來了沒有？
He should be back soon.
就快回來了
The German attack cut the lines. That's why he's late.
德軍切斷路線，所以他才遲了
Can we go outside?
我們出一出去好嗎？
I wrote to my mother about you.
我寫信向母親談起你
She wanted me to tell you that once this war was over,
她說，戰事結束之後
if there's anything you needed- anything at all...
無論你有什麼需要…
...our family will be there for you.
我們一家都會幫你
You know I'm here for you.
我一定會幫你
They're saying Vassili is dead.
他們說瓦西堣w經死了
Vassili Zaitsev will never see his loved ones again.
瓦西埵A也見不到親人了
Surrender! This is your only hope.
投降吧！投降是你們唯一希望
You're upset.
你難過？
Because Zaitsev is dead?
因為瓦西埵漱F？
You don't have to hide it. There's no shame in it.
不用掩飾，不用難為情
You're a Russian like he is.
你跟他一樣是俄羅斯人
Don't listen to them.
不要聽他們說
It's just propaganda.
這只是宣傳
He isn't dead.
他沒有死
And do you know why?
你知道原因嗎？
Because I haven't killed him yet.
因為我還沒有殺死他
I'm going to tell you a little secret.
告訴你一個秘密吧
Only you, because I know I can trust you.
我只告訴你，因為我信得過你
But you must swear to me that you won't tell another soul.
不過，你要發誓保密
You swear?
你肯不肯發誓？
I found a terrific spot.
我找到一個頂瓜瓜的地點
It's by the exit from the train station.
是火車站的出口旁邊
I'll hide in the water tower.
我會躲在水塔堶
Tomorrow. I'll wait for him there.
明天我等他來
You'll see. He'll be there.
他一定會來，你等著瞧吧
He always is.
他一直都會出現
I also want you to swear that from now on, you'll stay home where you belong.
我也要你發誓，從此你留在家
Do you swear? Yes?
你肯發誓嗎？肯嗎？
Good.
好
"We know he's alive. We know he won't fail us.
瓦西媮椄△菕A不會教我們失望
We know because he is a part of us now. Vassili is eternal."
因為他現在就在我們當中 瓦西堨握ㄕ
Where have you been? We've looked everywhere for you.
你去了哪堙H我們到處找你
Oh, didn't you hear? I was dead.
你沒聽到？我死了
At least the noble sniper Zaitsev...
起碼崇高的神射手瓦西堙K
Vassili was dead.
已經死去
The real one.
真正的瓦西堙K
Me...
我…
I was asleep,
我睡著了…
and I missed my chance.
錯失了機會
Then, I was curled up in a corner, hiding...
瑟縮在一角，躲避一個…
from a man who wants to kill me.
想置我於死地的人
I'll talk to Kruschev.
我會向赫魯曉夫報告
He'll send you back to your old division.
他會把你調回原本的部隊
Where's Tania? She's at the shelter.
坦妮亞呢？她在防空洞
I've been to the shelter.
我到過防空洞
I told her you weren't dead.
我對她說你沒死
The major said so. He said the other Germans were lying.
少校是這樣說 他說其他德軍在騙人
He told me you were waiting for him at the station.
他說你會在車站等他
Vassili.
瓦西堙K
My little Sacha.
我的小沙查…
I knew it.
不出我所料
Vassili. Tania.
- 瓦西 - 坦妮亞
I knew you weren't dead.
我早知你沒有死
How?
你怎知道？
Because we only just met.
因為我們才剛遇上
I prayed for the first time since I was a little girl.
我長大之後首次祈禱
When I opened my eyes, Sacha was standing there...
我一睜開眼睛…沙查就站在我面前
waiting to give me the good news.
報告好消息
I think he loves you even more than I do.
他比我更愛你呢
To the proper military authority,
致司令
I'm calling to the commandant's attention the recent changes noticed...
茲呈報士兵瓦西堙K
in the attitude towards fighting of soldier Vassili Zaitsev.
近來作戰態度改變了
He has attempted on several occasions to escape his duties,
數度試圖逃避職責
voiced doubts on the chances of our victory...
公開發表悲觀言論
and made defeatist comments in public.
懷疑祖國不能獲勝
The inexplicable duration of his duel...
他與納粹槍手決鬥，久不能獲勝
with the Nazi sharpshooter can only be explained by...
原因只可能是…
his lack of belief in the communist ideal.
他對共產理念缺乏信心
Good morning, Sacha.
早晨，沙查
Once again, he knew exactly where to find me.
他再一次知道我的行蹤
Don't you think that's strange?
你說奇不奇怪？
Apart from me, only you knew.
我的行蹤，只有你知我知
I don't hold it against you, Sacha.
我不怪你
You've done a very brave thing.
你很勇敢
You've chosen your camp. I respect that.
你選擇了陣營，我尊重你的選擇
But it isn't my camp.
但那不是我的陣營
We're both soldiers,
你我都是軍人
and we're both enemies, so I know you understand.
你我是敵人，我知道你會明白的
I'm annoyed with you, little Sacha, for not staying home as I made you swear to.
我生你氣，因為你不留在家
I'm annoyed with you for obliging me to do what I'm going to have to do.
我生你氣，因為你逼我做一件事
I've never seen anyone frown so much in their sleep.
你連睡夢中也皺眉頭
How long have you been watching me?
你看了我多久？
All night.
整晚
You've been snoring away happily for hours.
你不斷扯鼻鼾
I don't snore. Do I?
我扯鼻鼾？
Like a pig.
像豬一樣
I suppose I talk in my sleep as well.
我大概也有發開口夢吧？
Yes.
是的
There's something I should tell you.
有件事我想告訴你
On the train...
我坐火車來這堛漁伬唌K
we were in the same car.
和你在同一個車廂
No.
不可能
I saw you.
我見到你
You were reading, and you fell asleep.
你在看書，然後睡著了
I didn't dare look at you, you were so beautiful.
我不敢看你，你太漂亮了
It was scary.
很驚人
Afterwards, I couldn't stop thinking about you.
之後，我不斷想起你
It made me smile.
想起你就笑
And then I thought of all the men who would get to hold you...
又想到那些可以擁抱你
who'd make you laugh...
逗你發笑的人
how lucky they were.
他們是多麼的幸運
And now I'm the one lying next to you.
現在我居然可以躺在你身邊
Was I snoring? Like a pig.
- 我有沒有扯鼻鼾？ - 像豬一樣
What?
什麼事？
Oh, my God! Oh, no.
我的天！不要出去！
Oh, my God! Tania, no.
坦妮亞，
Tania, no! No, get off me!
不可以！
Get off me! Get off me! It's what he wants!
放開我！
This is what he wants! Get off me!
這正是他的目的！
No, he'll kill you. He'll kill you! Let me go!
- 他會殺死你 - 放手！
I'll run after you, and he'll kill me. Let me go!
我跟你出去，他也會殺死我
Let me go! This is what he wants! I'll get him.
- 放開我！ - 這正是他的目的
I promise I'll get him.
我保證會殺死他
I'll get his rifle for you. I promise, Tania.
我保證會拿他的槍給你
I need you.
我需要你幫忙
You have to leave now, Mrs. Filipov. Stalingrad may fall.
你必須走，斯大林格勒可能淪陷
The last of the boats are leaving. The Germans will be here any moment.
最後的船快開了，德軍隨時攻到
He's brought you a pass. You'll be safe on the other side.
我們替你弄到通行證 你在對岸會很安全
Gather your things, and we'll help you carry them to the landing stage.
收拾行李，我們送你去碼頭
I'm not leaving. This is my home.
我不走，這是我的家
This is my Sacha's home. I can't leave.
這是沙查的家，不可以走
I have to tell you something, Mrs. Filipov.
我有件事要告訴你
Something very difficult to understand.
這件事難以明白
It's about Sacha.
關於沙查的
He's gone over to the Germans. He's betrayed his country.
沙查投靠了德軍，出賣了國家
He's with the enemy now. He won't be coming back.
他現在跟德軍一起，不會回來了
Oh, my God.
我的天！
He's become a traitor.
他做了叛徒
The poor little thing.
可憐的小鬼頭
What has he done?
他做了什麼？
So, he's going to stay over there?
那麼，他會留在那邊？
Yes... he's going to stay over there.
是的 他會留在那邊
I shouldn't be saying this, comrade Commissar,
政委同志，我不應該這樣說
but maybe it's for the best.
不過，這樣或者更好
If the Germans have won, he'll be safe.
假如德軍打勝，他會安全
I know it's wrong, but perhaps he has made the right choice.
或者對他來說，這是正確選擇
Oh! Oh, Tania! Tania?
坦妮亞！ 坦妮亞！
I need a doctor! A doctor!
有沒有醫生？醫生！
I have a pass. I have a pass!
我有通行證
You must let her cross.
你一定要讓她上船！
Please!
求求你
It's useless. She'll never make it. No! No, she will!
- 沒用的，她不會活得成 - 她會！
She's my daughter! She's my daughter!
她是我女兒
I beg of you! All right.
- 求求你！ - 好吧
Oh, thank you! Put this one on the boat.
你們兩個，抬她上船
Where is he?
他在哪堙H
Where's the major?
少校在哪堙H
A few inches from your face.
咫尺之間
I've been such a fool, Vassili.
我一直都很愚昧，瓦西
Man will always be man.
人性改不了
There is no new man.
世上不會出現新人類
We tried so hard to create a society that was equal,
我們努力去創造平等社會
where there'd be nothing to envy your neighbor.
希望大家不用妒忌別人
But there's always something to envy.
可是，人總有令別人妒忌的東西
A smile...
一個微笑
a friendship.
一份友誼
Something you don't have and want to appropriate.
求之而不可得的東西
In this world- even a Soviet one-
在這世上，即使是蘇聯的世界…
there will always be rich and poor.
總是有富有貧
Rich in gifts...
富於天賦
poor in gifts.
貧於天賦
Rich in love...
富於愛情
poor in love.
貧於愛情
Tania isn't coming back.
坦妮亞不會回來了
She's dead, Vassili.
她死了
She was cut down by shrapnel. It was quick.
給炮彈碎片擊中
I don't think she even saw it coming.
事出突然，她該沒看到碎片飛來
She was on her way back to you.
她本來回來找你
As soon as she had seen Mrs. Filipov to the boats, she was coming back for you.
把費太太送上船之後馬上回來找你
She was right. You're a good man, Vassili.
她是對的，瓦西堙A你是個好人
I want to help you, Vassili.
我想幫你一個忙
Let me do one last thing.
我想做最後一件事
Something useful for a change.
試做有助改變的事
Let me show you where the major is.
我幫你找出少校的位置
Don't do that. Don't do that!
不要這樣做 不要！
Today, February3, 1943, is an ominous day for Hitler...
今天1943年2月3日…
and the endless columns of hundreds of thousands of German prisoners.
對希特勒和無數的德國戰俘而言是不祥的一天
It is an unforgettable day of hope for our motherland.
但卻是俄羅斯勝利難忘的一天
After 180 days of heroic combat...
經過了斯大林格勒180天
in the market city of Stalingrad,
奮勇的戰鬥
and as a result of the valor and self-sacrifice of our soldiers,
以及我軍奮不顧身的作戰
the commander of our glorious Red Army...
光榮的紅軍司令…
received the unconditional surrender...
接受了法西斯侵略者
of the German fascist invaders.
無條件投降
Sorry. No, young man, I cannot find...
對不起
a matching name in the book. Could you check again?
- 我找不到那個名字 - 請再找找
This is the address and her name. She is not here.
這是這醫院地址，這是她的名字
Yes, this is our address, but we don't have her anymore.
地址沒錯，但她不在這
This is the address. She's been here. I'm so sorry.
- 這是你們的地址 - 很對不起
She wrote to me. I looked three times. She's not here.
- 她寫過信給我 - 我查過三次了，她不在這
Believe me, there is no Tania Chernova. I can't help you.
我們的確沒有坦妮亞這個人 我們愛莫能助，
I'm so sorry.
對不起